<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title><![CDATA[Matthieu Moquet (@MattKetmo) - Personal Pages]]></title>
  <link href="https://moquet.net/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://moquet.net/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-23T09:43:11+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://moquet.net/</id>
      <author>
      <name><![CDATA[Matthieu Moquet]]></name>      <email><![CDATA[matthieu@moquet.net]]></email>    </author>
    <generator uri="http://sculpin.io/">Sculpin</generator>
      <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Smoothly migrate to ramsey/uuid 3.x]]></title>
      <link href="https://moquet.net/blog/smoothly-migrate-to-ramsey-uuid-3"/>
      <updated>2015-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://moquet.net/blog/smoothly-migrate-to-ramsey-uuid-3</id>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When dealing with UUID generation in PHP, developers usually decide to use the famous <a href="https://github.com/ramsey/uuid">ramsey/uuid</a> library.
95% of the time the only method used is <code>Ramsey\Uuid\Uuid::uuid4()</code> which generates a random UUID (the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Universally_unique_identifier#Version_4_.28random.29">version 4</a> in the UUID specification). Despite I'm not fan of static methods, this does the job pretty well.</p>

<h2 id="the-namespace-issue">The namespace issue</h2>

<p>A lot of applications and libraries started to use <code>ramsey/uuid</code> in version 2. At that time the package had a different name (<code>rhumsaa/uuid</code>) and every class was under the <code>Rhumsaa</code> namespace.
<a href="https://github.com/ramsey">Ben Ramsey</a> renamed the package first (the <code>rhumsaa/uuid</code> name is now deprecated) but only changed namespace since version 3.0. Which means libraries started using the <code>ramsey/uuid</code> with version 2.x (the <code>Rhumsaa</code> namespace) and make it incompatible with version 3.x (the <code>Ramsey</code> namespace).</p>

<p>Thus if you want to use <code>ramsey/uuid: ^3.0</code> but one of your dependencies is still using version <code>2.x</code> then you're screwed.
If the package <code>ramsey/uuid</code> was created for versions <code>3.0+</code> <strong>only</strong> we could have had both requirements (like Guzzle did between version 3 and 4). But unfortunatly that's not the case.</p>

<p>Updating version of <code>ramsey/uuid</code> in a project is an easy task: just grep and sed the <code>Rhumsaa</code> namespace. But if you change the requirements on a library which uses it on its public API, then you're creating a <strong>non-BC change</strong> and need to publish a new major version of your library. That change may have huge impact on users who depend on it. And if those users depend on another lib which requires a different version of the uuid lib then it's a mess. They will need to coordinate all updates at the same time.</p>

<p>However it looks pretty easy to resolve this issue. We "just" need to ensure the <code>Rhumsaa\Uuid\Uuid</code> class still exists.</p>

<h2 id="the-hack">The hack</h2>

<p>To address this issue I created a tiny composer package which exposes the <code>Rhumsaa\Uuid\Uuid</code> class (which simply inherit of <code>Ramsey\Uuid\Uuid</code>) and declares to composer it can replace the <code>ramsey/uuid:2.x</code> package. The package is available at <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/uuid-2x-bridge"><code>mattketmo/uuid-2x-bridge</code></a>.</p>

<p>Then if you want to use <code>ramsey/uuid:^3.0</code> in your app but one of your dependencies is still using <code>Rhumsaa\Uuid\Uuid</code>, then simply run:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">composer require "mattketmo/uuid-2x-bridge:*@dev"
</code></pre>

<p>Note that will only works if the libraries just need the main <code>Uuid</code> class. For Doctrine type and console component the packages <a href="https://github.com/ramsey/uuid-doctrine"><code>uuid-doctrine</code></a> and <a href="https://github.com/ramsey/uuid-console"><code>uuid-console</code></a> can be installed separately.</p>

<p>You can read the discussion in this <a href="https://github.com/prooph/common/pull/47">pull request</a> which led me to do this hack. It's not very beautiful, but it works.</p>

<h2 id="a-note-on-package-dependencies">A note on package dependencies</h2>

<p>Now that users have a way to not wait their dependencies update the <code>ramsey/uuid</code> requirement, all libraries can take the time for their next major version release to do the update.</p>

<p>But I want to point out the risk for library maintainers to depend on specific version of a package.
If you own a widly used library, try as much a possible to not require other libraries directly. Most of the time an abstraction or an adapter will be enough. For instance the team behind the <a href="https://github.com/qandidate-labs/broadway">Broadway</a> library created the <a href="https://github.com/qandidate-labs/broadway-uuid-generator">broadway-uuid-generator</a> to not depend direclty on Ramsey's implementation (and also to not rely on a static method call).</p>

<p>Even if it won't work for every usage, try to minimalize that risk. Ultimately that's what some <a href="http://www.php-fig.org/psr/psr-3/">P</a><a href="http://www.php-fig.org/psr/psr-6/">S</a><a href="http://www.php-fig.org/psr/psr-7/">R</a> are for, <a href="http://cdn.meme.am/instances/500x/63628685.jpg">isn't it?</a> ;).</p>

<p>In other words, <strong>think twice before forcing to your users a new dependency</strong>.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
      <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Realtime geolocation tracking with Firebase]]></title>
      <link href="https://moquet.net/blog/realtime-geolocation-tracking-firebase"/>
      <updated>2015-04-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://moquet.net/blog/realtime-geolocation-tracking-firebase</id>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I went recently to Google Paris offices to attend an <a href="http://www.meetup.com/AngularJS-Paris/events/221083701/">Angular meetup</a>
sponsorised by <a href="https://www.firebase.com/">Firebase</a>.
Although I've already heard about Firebase in the past (mainly when they got <a href="https://www.firebase.com/blog/2014-10-21-firebase-joins-google.html">acquired by Google</a>)
I've never tried it myself to see what it is capable of.
Here is a quick experiment I did to play with it.</p>

<p class="banner-container">
  <img
    class="Image center responsize isRounded"
    src="/uploads/blog/2015-04-16-realtime-geolocation-tracking-firebase/locatme-banner.png"
    alt="Locat.me banner"/>
</p>

<h2 id="firebase">Firebase</h2>

<p>Firebase is a <strong>Database as a Service</strong> which lets you <strong>store and synchronize</strong> data in (near) real-time.</p>

<p>As it focuses mostly on frontend and mobile apps you will find an <strong>SDK</strong> for Android, iOS and JavaScript.
But it also exposes a <strong>REST API</strong> so you can do basic CRUD operations from your backend.</p>

<p>The SDK allows you to establish a connection to their backend and receive notifications as soon as
data is updated. By "real-time" they ensure you to receive those events in less than 200ms.
They use <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/fr/docs/WebSockets">WebSockets</a> if available or fallback
to long polling if not.</p>

<p>They also propose other features like <a href="https://www.firebase.com/docs/web/guide/offline-capabilities.html">offline capabilities</a>
(similar to what PouchDB offers) and delegated Authentication (via Google/Twitter/Facebook connect).
I won't go much into details but invite you to <a href="https://www.firebase.com/docs/">read the docs</a>
or signup to try the <a href="https://www.firebase.com/how-it-works.html">quick tutorial</a> for more details.</p>

<h2 id="introducing-locat.me">Introducing Locat.me</h2>

<p>By using such technology you can develop an Uber-like application very easily, they said.
I was eager to test it.
Their admin dashboard is quite intuitive and the API is so simple that you can do powerful
thing quickly.</p>

<p>My proof of concept is very basic but it may be useful in some situations.</p>

<p>It's an app you can use to <strong>easily locate your friends</strong> when you have an appointment
but you don't have an accurate meeting point.
You know they are close but you have difficulties in explaining where you are exactly
(it could be a parallel street or just somewhere else in the park).</p>

<p>How the app works is very simple:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>go to</strong> <a href="http://locat.me/">locat.me</a> with a browser and <strong>accept</strong> to share your current position
(it uses the HTML5 <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Geolocation/Using_geolocation">Geolocation API</a>)</li>
<li><strong>copy</strong> the URL (a unique id has been generated in the hash) and <strong>send</strong> it to your friend
(eg. use the "Share" option from your browser to send an SMS)</li>
</ul>

<p>And that's it!</p>

<p>Now each time someone will go on that URL a new (anonymous) marker will be added
and the map will be refreshed without you do anything.
Blue point is your position while orange ones are others.</p>

<p>
  <a href="/uploads/blog/2015-04-16-realtime-geolocation-tracking-firebase/locatme-screenshot.png">
    <img
      class="Image center responsize"
      src="/uploads/blog/2015-04-16-realtime-geolocation-tracking-firebase/locatme-screenshot.png"
      alt="Locat.me Screenshot"
      width="300px" />
  </a>
</p>

<p>You can also use a custom identifier to share. Useful for named events
(for instance <a href="http://locat.me/#my_meetup">locat.me/#my_meetup</a> or even <a href="http://locat.me/#MattKetmo">locat.me/#MattKetmo</a>)</p>

<div class="note warning">
  <p>
    Note that since I'm using the free hacker plan of Firebase the maximum of
    connected users simultaneously is limited to 50.
  </p>
</div>

<div class="note info">
  <p>
    About the domain name, this is a gift from Gandi which offered some free domains for their 15th birthday.
    As I won a <code>.me</code> I decided to use it for that occasion (unfortunatly every cool and short domain names
    were already taken so I needed to sacrifice the final "e" letter).
  </p>
</div>

<h2 id="just-code-it">Just code it</h2>

<p>Now that I explained the main idea it's time to play with it.
The code is really trivial.
I think it took me less than an hour while watching a stupid movie on TV to get something working.</p>

<p>To display the map and the markers I used <a href="https://www.mapbox.com/">Mapbox</a>.
First time I played with it too.
But my usage is very simple. This is what I just need to know:</p>

<pre><code class="js">// Load the map canvas in the #map block
var map = L.mapbox.map('map', 'examples.map-i86nkdio')

map.on('ready', function() {

  // Add a new marker on the map
  var marker = L.marker([latitude, longitude]).addTo(map)

  // Update the marker position
  marker.setLatLng([latitude, longitude])

})
</code></pre>

<p>Second thing I need to handle is the URL hash (ie. the map identifier).
Here I just generate a new one unless it already exists.</p>

<pre><code class="js">// Read the current hash
var mapId = location.hash.replace(/^#/, '');

// If not set generate a new one
if (!mapId) {
  mapId = (Math.random() + 1).toString(36).substring(2, 12);
  location.hash = mapId;
}
</code></pre>

<p>This hash will help me to group markers together.
I will use Firebase to read and write the geolocations under the <code>/maps/{mapId}</code> endpoint.</p>

<p>
  <a href="/uploads/blog/2015-04-16-realtime-geolocation-tracking-firebase/screenshot-firebase-admin.png">
    <img
      class="Image center responsize"
      src="/uploads/blog/2015-04-16-realtime-geolocation-tracking-firebase/screenshot-firebase-admin.png"
      alt="Firebase admin screenshot"
      style="max-height:550px" />
  </a>
</p>

<p>As you can see on this admin panel screenshot every marker is stored under the path
<code>/maps/{mapId}/{markerId}</code>. It has a <code>coord</code> attribute with a latitude and a longitude
as well as a timestamp to know its last update date.</p>

<p>I've also set the security rules to avoid people fetching every map ids.
You can only read and write on path <code>/maps/{mapId}</code> but not directly on <code>/maps</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
  "rules": {
    "maps": {
      "$map": {
        ".read": true,
        ".write": true
      }
    }
  }
}
</code></pre>

<p>The marker identifiers are unique per browser.
I used a simple UUID generator function and save it in current <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Storage/LocalStorage">LocalStorage</a>.
It allows user to refresh the page without creating another marker on the map.</p>

<pre><code class="js">// Get current UUID
var myUuid = localStorage.getItem('myUuid');

// Create a new one for newcomers
if (!myUuid) {
  myUuid = guid();
  localStorage.setItem('myUuid', myUuid);
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now the main action is to get user's current location and store it on Firebase.
I'm using the HTML5 Geolocation API which provide a <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/API/Geolocation/Using_geolocation#Watching_the_current_position">watch function</a>
to be notified of his positions.</p>

<pre><code class="js">// Access to Firebase instance of current map
var markersRef = new Firebase('https://locatme.firebaseio.com/maps/' + mapId);

// Current position is stored under `myUuid` node
navigator.geolocation.watchPosition(function(position) {
  markersRef.child(myUuid).set({
    coords: {
      latitude: position.coords.latitude,
      longitude: position.coords.longitude,
    },
    timestamp: Math.floor(Date.now() / 1000)
  })
})
</code></pre>

<p>Now the only thing left is to add markers on the map.
To do this I listen on every events happening on the current map endpoint.
In the example below <code>addPoint()</code>, <code>putPoint()</code> and <code>removePoint()</code> are
simple functions to add, update or remove a marker in the map.</p>

<pre><code class="js">markersRef.on('child_added', function(childSnapshot) {
  var uuid = childSnapshot.key()
  var position = childSnapshot.val()

  addPoint(uuid, position)
})

markersRef.on('child_changed', function(childSnapshot) {
  var uuid = childSnapshot.key()
  var position = childSnapshot.val()

  putPoint(uuid, position)
})

markersRef.on('child_removed', function(oldChildSnapshot) {
  var uuid = oldChildSnapshot.key()

  removePoint(uuid)
})
</code></pre>

<p>That's pretty much it. It was easy, right?</p>

<p>If you want to hack on it, checkout the code on <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/firemap/blob/v1.0.0/app.js">github.com/MattKetmo/firemap</a>.
You can also find other demo applications of Firebase at <a href="https://firebase.github.io/">firebase.github.io</a>,
like this <a href="https://geofire.firebaseapp.com/sfVehicles/index.html">real-time bus tracking in San Francisco</a>.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
      <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[SymfonyCon Warsaw 2013 in a nutshell]]></title>
      <link href="https://moquet.net/blog/symfonycon-warsaw-2013"/>
      <updated>2013-12-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://moquet.net/blog/symfonycon-warsaw-2013</id>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first <a href="http://warsaw2013.symfony.com/">SymfonyCon</a>
in Warsaw has just finished, and I must admit that was great.
Congrats to the SensioLabs team and especially
<a href="https://twitter.com/ansobach">Anne-Sophie</a> for the organization.
The <a href="http://warsaw2013.symfony.com/venue">venue was incredible</a>
with a <a href="https://twitter.com/kriswallsmith/status/411050365753507840">big conference room</a>,
and more than 600 people were attending the main talks.
First time a Symfony conference is sold out more than two weeks before the due date.</p>

<p>Here is an extract of the notes I took during those two days.
As usual, talks were splitted into two tracks.
So I have nothing to say for half ones, except a link to the <strong>slides</strong>.</p>

<p><em>By the way, if you find a typo, feel free to <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/moquet.net/blob/gh-pages/_posts/2013-12-13-symfonycon-warsaw-2013.markdown">fork and edit this post</a>,
or <a href="https://twitter.com/MattKetmo">ping me on Twitter</a>.
Thank you!</em></p>

<h2 id="opening-keynote">Opening keynote</h2>

<p><em>Fabien Potencier</em> — <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/fabpot/symfonycon-2013-keynote">slides</a></p>

<p>It's a ritual, every Symfony conference starts by <a href="https://twitter.com/fabpot">fabpot</a>'s keynote.
Fabien began with some statistics about famous PHP libraries around
the Symfony ecosystem, and reminded us last features of the <a href="http://symfony.com">symfony.com</a>
website like the <a href="http://symfony.com/projects">projects page</a>,
the easy way to edit page and the <a href="http://symfony.com/roadmap">roapmap notifications</a>.</p>

<p>Then, as the Symfony "<a href="https://twitter.com/fabpot/status/6619944506630144">lead merger</a>",
he spoke about his way to process pull-requests on GitHub.
He wrote a <code>gh</code> command-line with nice features like the ability to change PRs'
destination branch — you know, bug fixes must be done on the oldest
maintained branch while new features on master —, squash git commits,
update commit message with a label and add the full issue thread.
This looks to be an amazing swiss knife and I hope it will be open-sourced shortly.</p>

<p>Lastly, he introduces the launch of a new tool called <a href="http://ubot.io">ubot.io</a>
— <em>edit 2013-12-18:</em> it has been renamed to <a href="http://fabbot.io/">fabbot.io</a>.
This is mainly an automatisation tool to detect typos and CS on pull-requests.
Think of it as bot combining both <a href="https://github.com/stof">stof</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/pborreli">pborreli</a> super powers.</p>

<p>Then two others speakers did a brief talk during the keynote:
<a href="https://twitter.com/javiereguiluz">Javier Eguiluz</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/julienPauli">Julien Pauli</a>
who both joined SensioLabs recently.</p>

<p>Javier mainly spoted five ideas to improve the Symfony community via its website:</p>

<ul>
<li>Improve the <a href="http://symfony.com/download">Symfony download experience</a></li>
<li>Unify conversations from GoogleGroup to GitHub</li>
<li>Merge all less known blogs (eg. Twig, Swiftmailer) into <a href="http://symfony.com/blog/">symfony.com/blog</a></li>
<li>Create new pages for communities, with members &amp; events</li>
<li>Avoid having too much bundle for one thing — this is currently a (top-secret) project
in progress and did not expand much on this topic</li>
</ul>

<p>Julien, the release manager of PHP 5.5 and ex-collegue from <a href="http://www.blablacar.com">BlaBlaCar</a>,
talked about the performance part he's going to focus on.
He's actually working on a rewrite of the Pimple library.
Some improvements had been made on the PHP code, but he's also working
on C-extensions to handle the low level parts. This is not a total rewrite of
the PHP library into a C library, but rather a hook of the slowest parts — like
does the <a href="http://twig.sensiolabs.org/doc/installation.html#installing-the-c-extension">C-extension of Twig</a>.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-automatize-your-infrastructure-with-chef">How to automatize your infrastructure with Chef</h2>

<p><em>Grégoire Pineau</em> — <a href="http://lyrixx.github.io/SFCon-Warsaw2013-Automation/">slides</a></p>

<p>This was an interesting talk about the existing tools you can use
to automatise your deployment workflow. There are many way to deploy
an application, whether it is done from your laptop or a dedicated server.
With such tools, you avoid human errors and better focus on business values.
The keys are to deploy small changeset, deploy often, and use <a href="http://marc.weistroff.net/2012/01/09/simple-feature-flags-symfony2">feature flags</a>
to deploy partially.</p>

<p>Several tools were mentionned:
- <a href="https://github.com/capistrano/capistrano">Capistrano</a>, plus <a href="http://capifony.org/">Capifony</a> to deploy easily
- <a href="http://fabfile.org">Fabric</a>, usefull for repetitive tasks or one-shot batch command
- <a href="http://www.ansibleworks.com/">Ansible</a>
- <a href="http://www.getchef.com/chef/">Chef</a> and <a href="http://puppetlabs.com/">Puppet</a> two (more or less equivalent) provisioning tools
- <a href="http://www.vagrantup.com/">Vagrant</a> to provision virtual machines
  (don't forget <a href="http://www.whitewashing.de/2013/08/19/speedup_symfony2_on_vagrant_boxes.html">this tip</a>
  when using Symfony2)</p>

<p>Grégoire is currently using Chef to deploy at SensioLabs.
I would like to have more concret examples but one talk wouldn't be enough.</p>

<h2 id="diving-deep-into-twig">Diving deep into Twig</h2>

<p><em>Matthias Noback</em> — <a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/matthiasnoback/diving-deep-into-twig">slides</a></p>

<h2 id="build-awesome-rest-apis-with-symfony2">Build Awesome REST APIs With Symfony2</h2>

<p><em>William Durand</em>, <em>Lukas Kahwe Smith</em> — <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/willdurand/build-awesome-rest-apis-with-symfony2">slides</a></p>

<p>Here William and Lukas showed us how to build a REST API using
some Symfony bundles and PHP libraries:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/schmittjoh/JMSSerializerBundle">JMSSerializerBundle</a>:
a key component for serializing data into several formats</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/FriendsOfSymfony/FOSRestBundle">FOSRestBundle</a>:
like the <a href="https://github.com/sensiolabs/SensioFrameworkExtraBundle/">SensioExtraBundle</a>,
it provides some nice listeners to handle data serialization on kernel view event,
and an automatic routing generation</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/willdurand/BazingaHateoasBundle">BazingaHateoasBundle</a>:
to handle hypermedia links in response</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/hautelook/TemplatedUriBundle">HautelookTemplatedUriBundle</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/nelmio/NelmioApiDocBundle">NelmioApiBundle</a>:
to automatically generate a beautiful documentation from your code</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/liip/liipcacheControlBundle">LiipCacheControlBundle</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/willdurand/Negotiation">Negotiation</a>:
a content negociation library, to handle request format while not using the URI extension</li>
</ul>

<p>If you haven't already done it, I recomand you to read William's blog post
about <a href="http://williamdurand.fr/2012/08/02/rest-apis-with-symfony2-the-right-way/">doing a REST API with Symfony</a>.</p>

<h2 id="simplify-your-code-with-annotations">Simplify your code with annotations</h2>

<p><em>Piotr Pasich</em> — <a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/piotrpasich/simplify-your-code-with-annotations-symfonycon-warsaw-2013">slides</a></p>

<h2 id="increase-productivity-with-doctrine2-extensions">Increase productivity with Doctrine2 extensions</h2>

<p><em>Gediminas Morkevicius</em></p>

<p>Gediminas is the author of the <a href="https://github.com/l3pp4rd/DoctrineExtensions">DoctrineExtension library</a>.
Here he talked about some features of those extensions.
Personally, I didn't really enjoy this talk.
I don't know if he did not sleep for a week,
but the intonation in his voice was quite insupportable and made me almost sleep.
Also, as I already knew the library, I didn't learn that much.</p>

<h2 id="pitching-symfony-to-your-client">Pitching Symfony to your Client</h2>

<p><em>John La</em> — <a href="http://www.funnygarbage.com/pitchSymfony">slides</a></p>

<h2 id="how-kris-writes-symfony-apps">How Kris Writes Symfony Apps</h2>

<p><em>Kris Wallsmith</em> — <a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/kriswallsmith/how-kris-writessymfonyappssymfonycon">slides</a></p>

<p>Kris told us how he writes a Symfony application.
From a <code>composer create-project</code> to the code in a controller,
he shows all different steps he uses to do.
What I can say is that Kris loves annotations, MongoDB, thin controllers,
simple models, event listeners, and princesses.</p>

<p>He usually uses <a href="https://github.com/schmittjoh/JMSDiExtraBundle">JMSDiExtraBundle</a>
for DIC configuration, require.js for handling sort of DIC in JavaScript,
and prefers Voters than ACL (see also <a href="#drop_ace_use_voters">Marie's talk</a> about that topic).</p>

<p>Kris is very pleasant to listen, and even won the best speaker award.</p>

<h2 id="symfony2-content-management-in-40-minutes">Symfony2 Content Management in 40 minutes</h2>

<p><em>David Buchmann</em> — <a href="http://davidbu.ch/slides/20131212-symfonycon-cmf.html">slides</a>, <a href="https://github.com/dbu/conference-tutorial/pulls?direction=asc">code sample</a></p>

<h2 id="cool-like-frontend-developer%3A-grunt%2C-requirejs%2C-bower-and-other-tools">Cool like Frontend Developer: Grunt, RequireJS, Bower and other Tools</h2>

<p><em>Ryan Weaver</em> —
<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/weaverryan/cool-like-frontend-developer-grunt-requirejs-bower-and-other-tools-29177248">slides</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/knpuniversity/symfonycon-frontend">code sample</a></p>

<p>Today's tools for frontend guys are lots more evolved than 5 years ago.
Here Ryan taught us — the backend guys — how powerful they can be.
He did a great introduction to <a href="http://bower.io/">Bower</a>, <a href="http://requirejs.org/">RequireJS</a>,
and <a href="http://gruntjs.com/">Grunt</a>, all powered by NodeJS.</p>

<p>A lot of (new) information has been explained in a few time.
I think that may be a lot for people who never used it before, but even
if the speech was fast, Ryan is a good teacher.</p>

<p>Personally, I was looking forward this talk in order to know how other people
integrate such tools in a Symfony application. I must admit I'm getting
rid of Assetic and I will spend a bit more time configuring correctly
all the asset part in my applications.
If you're curious too, look at <a href="https://github.com/knpuniversity/symfonycon-frontend">Ryan's code example</a>
or even at this <a href="https://github.com/kbond/symfony-grunt-edition">Symfony Grunt Edition</a>
made in the meantime by Kevin Bond.</p>

<h2 id="community-building-with-mentoring%3A-what-makes-people-crazy-happy-to-work-on-an-open-source-project%3F">Community Building with Mentoring: What makes people crazy happy to work on an open source project?</h2>

<p><em>Cathy Theys</em> — <a href="https://github.com/YesCT/warsaw">slides</a></p>

<h2 id="async-php-with-react">Async PHP with React</h2>

<p><em>Jeremy Mikola</em> — <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jmikola/async-php-with-react">slides</a></p>

<p>Main purpose of this talk was to demonstrate how to build an event-driven
PHP application. You may know how NodeJS works via its "Event Loop" to get
non-blocking IO.
Here Jeremy exposed the basic architecture of such asynchronous
application and the way you can do it via processus.</p>

<p>PHP have the socket and stream APIs, but they're not very pleasant to use.
That's where <a href="http://reactphp.org/">ReactPHP</a> comes in. Keep in mind to always avoid
blocking IO when using React — which is not the default of most operations.</p>

<p>This was really a nice talk about async and IO vs. CPU, but sometimes a bit hard
to follow for <a href="http://www.memecenter.com/fun/144660/Alcohol-is-poison">a friday morning</a>.</p>

<h2 id="symfony2-forms%3A-past%2C-present%2C-future">Symfony2 Forms: Past, Present, Future</h2>

<p><em>Bernhard Schussek</em> — <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/bschussek/symfony2-forms-past-present-future">slides</a></p>

<h2 id="drop-ace%2C-use-voters">Drop ACE, use voters</h2>

<p><em>Marie Minasyan</em> — <a href="http://slid.es/marieminasyan/drop-ace-use-role-voters">slides</a></p>

<p>Marie did a great job on teaching the different methods to implement a
security access control in a standard Symfony app.
She first showed us how the Access Control Engine can be complicated.
Then she compared with a Voter implementation, which is much easier to code and test.</p>

<p>For French guys, I also recommend reading this
<a href="http://devblog.lexik.fr/non-classe/faciliter-la-gestion-des-droits-dacces-avec-les-voters-2488">blog post</a> from Lexik team,
or <a href="http://kriswallsmith.net/post/15994931191/symfony2-security-voters">this one</a> in English from Kris Wallsmith.</p>

<h2 id="proxy-pattern-in-php">Proxy pattern in PHP</h2>

<p><em>Marco Pivetta</em> — <a href="http://ocramius.github.io/presentations/proxy-pattern-in-php/#/">slides</a></p>

<h2 id="mastering-the-security-component%27s-authentication-mechanism">Mastering the Security component's authentication mechanism</h2>

<p><em>Joseph Rouff</em> — <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/rouffj/mastering-the-security-components-authentication-mechanism">slides</a>,
<a href="https://github.com/rouffj/HowtoSecurityBundle">code sample</a></p>

<p>Joseph made an excellent <em>live tutorial</em> on how to create your own security system.
This talk is very educational if you haven't looked deeply into the security
component. I strongly encourage you to view the (upcoming) video — or
<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eVaz_mMuDjw">this existing one</a> in French.</p>

<h2 id="symfony-components-in-the-wild">Symfony components in the wild</h2>

<p><em>Jakub Zalas</em> — <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jakzal/symfony-components-in-the-wild-symfonycon-2013">slides</a></p>

<h2 id="application-monitoring-with-heka-and-statsd">Application monitoring with Heka and statsd</h2>

<p><em>Jordi Boggiano</em> — <a href="http://slides.seld.be/?file=2013-12-13+Application+monitoring+with+Heka+and+statsd.html">slides</a></p>

<p>Jordi started quite recently to take an interest in application &amp; architecture monitoring.
Monitoring becomes more and more important when building complex apps with many "moving parts".
Lead developer of Composer, he presented us the tool he chose to monitor
<a href="http://packagist.org">packagist.org</a>.</p>

<p>Actually there are many tools on the market.
Each one serving a specific goal, for instance:
- System: Collectd, Cacti, Nagios, Ganglia, Munin
- Performance: Statsd, Sentry
- Error reporting: NewRelic
- Log aggregator: Graylog, Loggly, Splunk, Logstash, Syslog</p>

<p>It may be overkill to keep track of several tools.
That's why he chose to look at <a href="https://github.com/mozilla-services/heka">Heka</a>
in order to have only one (nice) dashboard with all metrics.</p>

<p>Heka is like a generic middleware which will be able to read from
many inputs (eg. syslog, nginx log, app log, etc.), apply some decoders and filters,
and then write to any datastore.
For instance all logs could be stored on elasticsearch and visualized via
the <a href="http://demo.kibana.org/">Kibana</a> UI.
Note that Heka can also be put on a cluster.</p>

<p>This project is relativly young, but in active development by Mozilla.
It worse keeping an eye on it.</p>

<h2 id="taming-runaway-silex-apps">Taming Runaway Silex Apps</h2>

<p><em>Dave Marshall</em> — <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/davedevelopment/taming-runaway-silex-apps-symfonycon-warsaw-2013">slides</a></p>

<h2 id="decouple-your-application-with-domain-events">Decouple your application with (Domain-)Events</h2>

<p><em>Benjamin Eberlei</em> — <a href="http://qafoo.com/talks/13_12_symfonycon_domain_events.pdf">slides</a></p>

<p>This talk was about avoiding high coupling &amp; legacy code.
This is quite a common subject nowaday.
Each developer try to find the best solution to write clean and decoupled code.
So did Kris in <a href="#how_kris_writes_symfony_apps">his previous talk</a>.
Here Benjamin explained his approach using the event dispatcher.</p>

<p>The main difficulty is to find the right boundaries between the different
parts of your application.
You must extract the different events that can occur.
Doing "event storming" with your team can help you a lot.</p>

<p>Also, avoid using services from other bundles, but prefer interfaces.
Every action of your controller should have a dedicated event.
Different approaches were suggested here, each with pros and cons.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-build-console-applications">How to build Console Applications</h2>

<p><em>Daniel Gomes</em> — <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/danielcsgomes/how-to-build-console-applications-symfonycon-2013">slides</a></p>

<h2 id="lighting-talks">Lighting Talks</h2>

<p>Lighting talks are good way to encourage developers to present their work.
There were a dizain of short speeches — less than 7 minutes each.</p>

<p>First talks were made par <a href="https://github.com/Sylius/Sylius">Sylius</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/Payum/Payum">Payum</a> lead developers.
We also have a speech about HTTP cache in ezPublish, and <a href="https://twitter.com/drrotmos">Magnus</a>
showed us a way to defer a process in your Symfony app with php-fpm using
<a href="https://github.com/fervo/FervoDeferredEventBundle">FervoDeferredEventBundle</a>.
Regarding fabpot, he spoiled us with futur improvements on the Console component
(<a href="https://speakerdeck.com/fabpot/symfonycon-2013-lightning-talk-about-the-console-in-2-dot-5">slides</a>).</p>

<p>Second day of lighting talks has started with
<a href="https://twitter.com/so_php_ie">Sophie Beaupuis</a> who made a demo
of a Zend software to easily package and deploy any PHP application.
Then Nicolas Grekas talked about the <a href="https://github.com/nicolas-grekas/Patchwork-UTF8">Patchwork-UTF8</a>
library, <a href="https://twitter.com/mmoreram">Marc Morera</a> introduced
the <a href="https://github.com/mmoreram/GearmanBundle">GearmanBundle</a>
(<a href="http://fr.slideshare.net/MarcMorera/gearman-bundle-warsaw-2013-ed">slides</a>),
and David de Boer explained his strategy to invalidate HTTP cache using
<a href="https://github.com/driebit/DriebitHttpCacheBundle">DriebitHttpCacheBundle</a>.
By the way, he started to work on a <a href="https://github.com/ddeboer/FOSHttpCacheBundle">new FOS bundle</a>
to combine both DriebitHttpCacheBundle and LiipCacheControlBundle.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/liuggio">Liuggio</a> talked about an important topic on <em>avoiding the monolithic</em>
using a decoupled, flexible and tailored architecture (<a href="http://www.slideshare.net/liuggio/leaphly-fight-monolothic-today">slides</a>).
I just looked over his <a href="http://welcometothebundle.com/">website</a> and saw several interessing posts.
He's also author of <a href="http://leaphly.org/">Leaphly</a>, a nice shopping cart for developer.</p>

<p>The lighting talks session has been closed by the amazing
Jeremy Mikola who spoke about… <em>lights</em>!
I can't describe his talk but that was very fun and very well played.
I hope there will be a video.</p>

<p>I won't talk about the award ceremony, and the hacking days which will be
covered on Symfony website. Thanks again for this huge event,
and see you next year in Madrid.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
      <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Distributing a PHP CLI app with ease]]></title>
      <link href="https://moquet.net/blog/distributing-php-cli"/>
      <updated>2013-07-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://moquet.net/blog/distributing-php-cli</id>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Something I love with PHP is how easily you can build a CLI application.
Some libraries like the Symfony Console Component has greatly
improved this process. Also, the ability to package a whole application
into a single PHAR container make the distribution and usage even
easier.</p>

<p>Such as <a href="http://getcomposer.org/"><code>composer</code></a> or <a href="http://cs.sensiolabs.org/"><code>php-cs-fixer</code></a>,
let's see how to quickly build a PHAR file for your application
with self-update capabilities.</p>

<h2 id="the-symfony-console">The Symfony Console</h2>

<p>First we need to create our CLI app. Let's call it <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/cliph">Cliph</a>.
For the example, we will build a typical <a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/index.html">Symfony console</a>
app with one « <em>hello world</em> » command.
Basically this results <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/cliph/commit/cd38f2438fe049033fe83d60c711d365cd68e261">in only 2 files</a>.
The first one is the command in the <code>src</code> folder:</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace Cliph\Command;

use Symfony\Component\Console\Command\Command;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Input\InputInterface;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Output\OutputInterface;

class HelloCommand extends Command
{
    protected function configure()
    {
        $this
            -&gt;setName('hello')
            -&gt;setDescription('Say hello')
        ;
    }

    protected function execute(InputInterface $input, OutputInterface $output)
    {
        $output-&gt;writeln('Hello World');
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>And the second is the launcher in <code>bin/cliph</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="php">#!/usr/bin/env php
&lt;?php

require __DIR__.'/../vendor/autoload.php';

use Cliph\Command;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Application;

$application = new Application('Cliph', '0.1-dev');
$application-&gt;add(new Command\HelloCommand());
$application-&gt;run();
</code></pre>

<p>Our application is now ready to run:</p>

<pre><code>$ ./bin/cliph --version
Cliph version 0.1-dev

$ ./bin/cliph hello
Hello World
</code></pre>

<h2 id="the-box-project">The Box Project</h2>

<p>The next step is to package all the sources into one single executable
<a href="http://www.php.net/manual/en/intro.phar.php">PHAR</a> file.</p>

<p>If you tried to build a PHAR file for your own CLI app, you may
already have read the <a href="https://github.com/composer/composer/blob/1.0.0-alpha7/src/Composer/Compiler.php"><code>Compiler.php</code> script from Composer</a>. This script
is launched via <code>./bin/compile</code> and produces the <code>composer.phar</code> file.</p>

<p>Now we want the same thing for our app, but without writing any line of PHP.
That would be redundant for each project.
This is where the <a href="http://box-project.github.io/box2/">Box Project</a> comes in.
The idea behing this tool is to replace the usual <code>compile</code> script with
a simple JSON file.</p>

<p>The JSON file contains the location of the PHP files to combine, and
the executable to run. This is typically what we need for our app:</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "chmod": "0755",
    "directories": [
        "src"
    ],
    "files": [
        "LICENSE"
    ],
    "finder": [
        {
            "name": "*.php",
            "exclude": ["Tests"],
            "in": "vendor"
        }
    ],
    "git-version": "package_version",
    "main": "bin/cliph",
    "output": "cliph.phar",
    "stub": true
}
</code></pre>

<p>As you notice, you can specify the source files using three different directives:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>directories</code>: to import a whole directory, typically the source folder</li>
<li><code>files</code>: ideal to import in single file — here the license</li>
<li><code>finder</code>: if you want more advanced filters, this use the
<a href="http://symfony.com/doc/current/components/finder.html">Symfony Finder component</a>.
This is very handy to exclude some useless files like the tests.</li>
</ul>

<p>Then come the options to customise the PHAR file. The <code>output</code> specifies
the name of the script; the <code>main</code> is the launcher script; we use <code>chmod</code>
to make it executable by default; and of course the <code>stub</code> must be enabled
for a CLI app.</p>

<p>Finally you may wonder what the <code>git-version</code> stands for. The value of this
parameter is used to replace any string in the source files. Here, any string
<code>@package_version@</code> is replaced by a version number based on the git
repository. To take advantage of this, we place it as the version parameter
on our main launcher <code>bin/cliph</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php
//...
$application = new Application('Cliph', '@package_version@');
</code></pre>

<p>Time to see the result. <a href="https://github.com/box-project/box2#as-a-phar-recommended">Install Box</a>
if you did not already, then run:</p>

<pre><code>$ box build
Building...
$ ./cliph.phar --version
Cliph version ad2fc07
</code></pre>

<p>Simple, isn't it? It's even better if use git tags to have a proper version number:</p>

<pre><code>$ git tag 1.0.0
$ box build
Building...
$ ./cliph.phar --version
Cliph version 1.0.0
</code></pre>

<p>Box will automatically use the git tag number if any, or fallback to the
commit hash. If a tag was created on a previous commit, the version may
look somthing like <code>1.0.0-1-gae87139</code> (ie. use of tag + commit hash).</p>

<h2 id="auto-updates">Auto updates</h2>

<div class="note info"><p>
<b>Edit Jan. 2016</b>: I now recommend you to also read this great blog post
<a href="https://mwop.net/blog/2015-12-14-secure-phar-automation.html">"Secure PHAR Automation"</a>
by <a href="https://twitter.com/mwop">@mwop</a> which makes use of the
<a href="https://github.com/padraic/phar-updater">padraic/phar-updater</a>
library and GitHub pages to automate and sign your PHAR file.
</p></div>

<p>Now that we have our PHAR, it would be awesome to add a command to auto update
the app. Think of something like <code>composer self-update</code>,
but as usual with minimal code.</p>

<p>The library which will help us this time is <a href="https://github.com/herrera-io/php-phar-update">php-phar-update</a>.
This library handles the whole update process.
To make it work, we need to instanciate a <code>Manager</code> object from a <code>Manifest</code>
then run the update method.
The <code>Manifest</code> contains all the possible updates. Ideally it
reads a remote JSON file which contains the list of all available versions.
To host the <code>manifest.json</code> file, we will use GitHub pages.</p>

<p>Here is what look like our update command:</p>

<pre><code class="php">&lt;?php

namespace Cliph\Command;

use Herrera\Phar\Update\Manager;
use Herrera\Phar\Update\Manifest;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Command\Command;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Input\InputInterface;
use Symfony\Component\Console\Output\OutputInterface;

class UpdateCommand extends Command
{
    const MANIFEST_FILE = 'http://mattketmo.github.io/cliph/manifest.json';

    protected function configure()
    {
        $this
            -&gt;setName('update')
            -&gt;setDescription('Updates cliph.phar to the latest version')
        ;
    }

    protected function execute(InputInterface $input, OutputInterface $output)
    {
        $manager = new Manager(Manifest::loadFile(self::MANIFEST_FILE));
        $manager-&gt;update($this-&gt;getApplication()-&gt;getVersion(), true);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Only two lines of code. Awesome, right? The first parameter of the <code>update</code>
method is the current version number (in order to compare with available versions),
while the second allows to download major version.
Here is the <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/cliph/commit/b3555f4c81f27002893845d96fb69a79f757f47d">full diff</a>
of that new update feature.</p>

<p>Let's tag our new functionnality, and re-build the PHAR:</p>

<pre><code>$ git tag 1.1.0

$ box build
Building...

$ ./cliph.phar
Cliph version 1.1.0

Available commands:
  hello   Say hello
  help    Displays help for a command
  list    Lists commands
  update  Updates cliph.phar to the latest version
</code></pre>

<p>Now we just have to put a <code>manifest.json</code>
plus the build PHAR into the <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/creating-project-pages-manually#lets-get-crackin"><code>gh-pages</code> branch</a>
and deploy it to GitHub. Note that I used the <code>openssl sha1 &lt;file&gt;</code> command to
get the hash of the PHAR file.</p>

<pre><code>$ cat manifest.json
[
    {
        "name": "cliph.phar",
        "sha1": "fbcded58df0ea838c17d56a5e3cdace56127d538",
        "url": "http://mattketmo.github.io/cliph/downloads/my-cli-1.1.0.phar",
        "version": "1.1.0"
    }
]
$ tree
.
├── downloads
│   └── cliph-1.1.0.phar
└── manifest.json
</code></pre>

<p>Yeah, we've just acheived the update command step.
To try it, let's upgrade Cliph version to 1.1.1 with that <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/cliph/commit/c808ae0b5467e6a0d3d91ba9ef75e492a4a4974a">new commit</a>,
and the corresponding <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/cliph/commit/e0744142c5b4fd1e454d45bdc31c6f2ffd62ea1c">manifest.json</a>.
Then, from a <code>1.1.0</code> vesion of our app, run the <code>update</code> command:</p>

<pre><code>$ ./cliph.phar --version
Cliph version 1.1.0

$ ./cliph.phar update
Updated to the latest version

$ ./cliph.phar --version
Cliph version 1.1.1
</code></pre>

<h2 id="sign-your-application">Sign your application</h2>

<p>Now as a bonus part, we would like to sign our application.
PHAR files can be signed with a set of public &amp; private keys — using for instance OpenSSL.
The archive is built with the private key, and to run the file
the public key must be put next to it:</p>

<p>« <em>If the phar archive is saved as <code>/path/to/my.phar</code>, the public key must be
saved as <code>/path/to/my.phar.pubkey</code>, or phar will be unable to verify the
signature.</em> » — <a href="http://php.net/manual/en/phar.using.intro.php">php.net</a></p>

<p>To generate an OpenSSL private key, you have choice to directly use the <code>openssl</code>
command, or the <code>box key:create</code>. Then, to sign the PHAR the only thing to do is
to add the <code>key</code> option into your <code>box.json</code> file:</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "chmod": "0755",
    "...": "...",
    "stub": true,
    "key": "private.key"
}
</code></pre>

<p>Then if you run a <code>box build</code> you will see a new file <code>cliph.phar.pubkey</code>.
If you try to move or remove this file, you will get a <code>PharException</code>.</p>

<p>Note that if you have set a passphrase for your private key, you must report
it in the <code>box.json</code> (<code>"key-pass": "mypass"</code>). But if you do so, please don't
version this file.
Instead use a <code>box.json.dist</code> and overwrite it in your local environment.
However I must admit I'm not really fan of that solution.
In my opinion, an option in the <code>box</code> command would be clever
(eg. <code>box build --key private.key -p</code>).</p>

<h2 id="automation">Automation</h2>

<p>Last thing we want to do is to automate the whole process.
For the example, I wrote a stupid <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/cliph/commit/5897c317f2a6a54208482540ef33d7316407a984">bash script</a>
which handle all the actions described in this post (git tag, box build, copy to gh-pages, update manifest).
It works with <a href="https://github.com/micha/jsawk"><code>jsawk</code></a> to manipulate the JSON file.</p>

<p>Now I just have to run:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ ./bump-version.sh 1.3.0
</code></pre>

<p>And a new PHAR file is automatically created with the given version number,
and pushed to the <code>gh-pages</code>.</p>

<p>Thus we've finally learned in a few steps how to make our CLI app easily distributable.
The Box project is really something you have to look at if you are
building PHAR files. And of course, you can adapt the "self-update" part to your need.
Big thanks to <a href="https://github.com/kherge">Kevin Herrera</a> for those tools,
that's very helpful.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
      <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[5 features to know about Composer PHP]]></title>
      <link href="https://moquet.net/blog/5-features-about-composer-php"/>
      <updated>2013-03-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://moquet.net/blog/5-features-about-composer-php</id>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are some tips you should know when using Composer the dependency manager for PHP.</p>

<h2 id="1.-update-only-one-vendor">1. Update only one vendor</h2>

<p>You want to update only one specific library, without updating all your
dependencies? That's easy, just add the vendor name as argument to the
<a href="http://getcomposer.org/doc/03-cli.md#update"><code>update</code></a> command:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ composer update foo/bar
</code></pre>

<p>This will only install or update the library (plus its dependencies) and
overwrite the <code>composer.lock</code>.</p>

<p>Nevertheless, this is also very usefull to fix a warning message I'm sure you
know very well:</p>

<p><code class="pre" style="background:#ffe680;color:#303030">
Warning: The lock file is not up to date with the latest changes in composer.json,
you may be getting outdated dependencies, run update to update them.
</code></p>

<p><em>« Damn it composer, what's wrong with my vendors? »</em>. Don't panic! This is
what you should expect if you just have edited the <code>composer.json</code> file. For
instance, if you <strong>add or update a detail</strong> like the library description,
authors, extra parameters, or even put a trailing whitespace, this will change
the <strong>md5sum</strong> of the file. Then Composer will warn you if this hash differs from
the one stored in the <code>composer.lock</code>.</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "hash": "0bcd1234f87401a9669eb5264b8e32a7",
    "packages": [
       "..."
    ]
}
</code></pre>

<p>Ok, so how to proceed? The <code>update</code> command is the one which update the lock file.
But if I just add a description, I may not want to update any library.
In that case use the <code>--lock</code> parameter.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ composer update --lock
</code></pre>

<p>Thus Composer won't upgrade your vendors.
It will <strong>only update the lock file hash</strong> to suppress the warning.
However it may also install the packages you have not yet installed
(if you have not done the <code>install</code> command previously), but no package upgrade is performed.</p>

<p>Note that trying to update a vendor that doesn't exist will have the same effect.</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ composer update foobar
</code></pre>

<h2 id="2.-add-a-library-without-editing-your-composer.json">2. Add a library without editing your composer.json</h2>

<p>To add a new vendor for your project, you can manually add a new line into your
<code>composer.json</code> then use the previous method to <strong>only</strong> install/update this vendor.
But there is a much convenient way to proceed.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://getcomposer.org/doc/03-cli.md#require"><code>require</code></a> command will make
those actions for you:</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ composer require "foo/bar:1.0.0"
</code></pre>

<p>If you omit to specify the version Composer will <strong>fetch the last stable</strong>.</p>

<p>This action can also be used to quickly start a new project. The
<a href="http://getcomposer.org/doc/03-cli.md#init"><code>init</code></a> command include the
<code>--require</code> option which will write the <code>composer.json</code> file with the given
vendor(s) (note the <code>-n</code> option to not ask any interactive question):</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ composer init --require="foo/bar:1.0.0" -n
$ cat composer.json
{
    "require": {
        "foo/bar": "1.0.0"
    }
}
</code></pre>

<h2 id="3.-easy-fork">3. Easy fork</h2>

<p>Speaking about <code>composer.json</code> initialization, did you ever used the
<a href="http://getcomposer.org/doc/03-cli.md#create-project"><code>create-project</code></a>
command?</p>

<pre><code class="bash">$ composer create-project doctrine/orm path 2.2.0
</code></pre>

<p>This will automatically clone the repository and checkout the given version.
That may be usefull to quickly clone a library without searching the original
URI of the sources.</p>

<h2 id="4.-prefer-dist-packages-and-cache-them">4. Prefer dist packages and cache them</h2>

<p>Did you know that <strong>dist packages are now cached</strong> in your home directory?</p>

<p>I previously <a href="/blog/proxify-composer-php/">wrote an article</a>
to compare solutions for caching vendors between multiple projects to save time
when cloning a repository. I even created <a href="https://github.com/mattketmo/stone">my own command</a> to clone vendors
into your global composer configuration to reuse it when necessary.</p>

<p>Since <a href="https://github.com/composer/composer/pull/1282">November 2012</a>, Composer
automatically stores the archive when you download a dist package. By default,
dist packages are used for tagged versions, for instance <code>"symfony/symfony":
"v2.1.4"</code>, or even a wildcard or range version like <code>"2.1.*"</code> or
<code>"&gt;=2.2,&lt;2.3-dev"</code> if you use <code>stable</code> as your <code>minimum-stability</code>.</p>

<p>But dist packages can also work with branches (ie. <code>dev-master</code>) as Github
allows to download an archive from a git reference. To force downloading
archive instead of cloning sources, use the <code>--prefer-dist</code> option included in
the <code>install</code> and <code>update</code> command.</p>

<p>Here is a demonstration (I use the <code>--profile</code> option to show the execution
time):</p>

<pre><code class="nohighlight">$ composer init --require="twig/twig:1.*" -n --profile
Memory usage: 3.94MB (peak: 4.08MB), time: 0s

$ composer install --profile
Loading composer repositories with package information
Installing dependencies
  - Installing twig/twig (v1.12.2)
    Downloading: 100%

Writing lock file
Generating autoload files
Memory usage: 10.13MB (peak: 12.65MB), time: 4.71s

$ rm -rf vendor

$ composer install --profile
Loading composer repositories with package information
Installing dependencies from lock file
  - Installing twig/twig (v1.12.2)
    Loading from cache

Generating autoload files
Memory usage: 4.96MB (peak: 5.57MB), time: 0.45s
</code></pre>

<p>Here, the archive for <code>twig/twig:1.12.2</code> has been stored into
<code>~/.composer/cache/files/twig/twig/1.12.2.0-v1.12.2.zip</code> and used the second
time I reinstalled the package.</p>

<h2 id="5.-prefer-source-to-edit-your-vendors">5. Prefer source to edit your vendors</h2>

<p>For practical reasons, you may prefer cloning sources instead of downloading
packages. For instance, this can be useful to edit a library directly in the
vendor directory to test the behaviour of your application with that change
(eg. a bug fix). The <code>--prefer-source</code> option will force cloning sources
instead of downloading an archive:</p>

<pre><code class="nohighlight">$ composer update symfony/yaml --prefer-source
</code></pre>

<p>Then to see modified files in your vendor:</p>

<pre><code class="nohighlight">$ composer status -v
You have changes in the following dependencies:
/path/to/app/vendor/symfony/yaml/Symfony/Component/Yaml:
    M Dumper.php
</code></pre>

<p>Composer will also tells you when you try to update a vendor that has been
modified, and asks if you want to discard the changes:</p>

<pre><code class="nohighlight">$ composer update
Loading composer repositories with package information
Updating dependencies
  - Updating symfony/symfony v2.2.0 (v2.2.0- =&gt; v2.2.0)
    The package has modified files:
    M Dumper.php
    Discard changes [y,n,v,s,?]?
</code></pre>

<h2 id="be-ready-for-production">Be ready for production</h2>

<p>Just a reminder, before deploying your code in production, don't forget to optimize
the autoloader:</p>

<pre><code class="nohighlight">$ composer dump-autoload --optimize
</code></pre>

<p>This can also be used while installing packages with the <code>--optimize-autoloader</code> option.
Without that optimization, you may notice a <a href="http://www.ricardclau.com/2013/03/apc-vs-zend-optimizer-benchmarks-with-symfony2/">performance loss from 20 to 25%</a>.</p>

<p>Of course, if you need any help or details for a command, read to the
<a href="http://getcomposer.org">official documentation</a> or watch this awesome
<a href="http://composer.json.jolicode.com/">interactive cheatsheet</a> made by JoliCode.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
      <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[Proxify Composer for PHP]]></title>
      <link href="https://moquet.net/blog/proxify-composer-php"/>
      <updated>2012-08-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://moquet.net/blog/proxify-composer-php</id>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every PHP developer who use modern libraries or frameworks should know
<a href="http://getcomposer.org/">Composer</a>. Composer is a dependency manager for PHP which allows you to
declare the dependent libraries your project needs and it will install them in
your project for you.</p>

<p>Unlike system like PEAR, Composer is only "project-aware". This means your
dependencies must be installed for each of your project. This is essential
because your projects can depend on different version of a same library. In the
other hand it can be quite painful to download or git-clone many times all the
vendors from a (far far away) remote server. This is especially true when you:</p>

<ul>
<li>are working on <strong>many projects</strong> at the same time</li>
<li>regulary <code>rm -rf vendor/</code> to be sure to <strong>remove</strong> the old dependencies (or
because Composer just got a bug :))</li>
<li>work on a project where everyone is using the same <strong>local network</strong> (that's
true when you work in a company)</li>
</ul>

<p>Since Composer approaches the date of the first stable version, the second
argument is becoming obsolete. Nevertheless, I want to focus on the last
point.</p>

<p>When you use a development version of a framework or library, you generally
want to get it from the sources. For instance, if you want to start a new
project with the 2.1 version of the <a href="http://symfony.com/">Symfony</a> fullstack framework (for now,
<code>2.1.*</code> is an alias for <code>dev-master</code>), you have to git-clone the sources from
GitHub. From an European network, it takes quite long to fetch a repository
hosted on a US server:</p>

<pre><code>$ time git clone git://github.com/symfony/symfony.git
Cloning into symfony...
remote: Counting objects: 140968, done.
remote: Compressing objects: 100% (43619/43619), done.
remote: Total 140968 (delta 89494), reused 132229 (delta 81990)
Receiving objects: 100% (140968/140968), 20.97 MiB | 198 KiB/s, done.
Resolving deltas: 100% (89494/89494), done.

real    2m15.30s
user    0m1.47s
sys     0m3.00s
</code></pre>

<p>More than 2 minutes is necessary to clone our main vendor (hopefully we don't
use SVN anymore). In addition to other libraries like <a href="https://github.com/doctrine/doctrine2">Doctrine</a> or <a href="http://github.com/fabpot/Twig">Twig</a>,
the installation of all vendors could easily take 5 minutes or more. The
objective of this article would be to find a solution to install the same
vendors, in less than 15 seconds.</p>

<p>This would be really usefull to <strong>save time and bandwidth</strong> not only for the
developers, but also for CI systems (<a href="http://jenkins-ci.org/">Jenkins</a>/<a href="http://travis-ci.org/">Travis</a>), or PaaS solution
like <a href="http://henrik.bjrnskov.dk/using-composer-on-pagodabox/">PagodaBox</a> or <a href="http://bergie.iki.fi/blog/using_composer_to_manage_dependencies_in_heroku_php_apps/">Heroku</a> which run a <code>composer install</code> each time you
deploy a new code.</p>

<p>As Git is a decentralized system, it is relativly easy to create a proxy ---
ie. a local clone of the repository --- which everyone could use instead of the
original one.</p>

<h2 id="using-gitpod">Using Gitpod</h2>

<p><a href="https://github.com/sitaramc/gitpod">Gitpod</a> is a local caching server for Git. Its operation is very simple:
once you've cloned a repository, each time you git-fetch it, it will git-fetch
the original repository first. Thus, the first time will be as long as you if
you git-fetched the original repository, while the second will be
instantaneous.</p>

<p>The following example shows how I set up Gitpod to work with Composer.</p>

<p>According to the <a href="https://github.com/sitaramc/gitpod#readme">documentation</a>,
you first need to create a <code>gp</code> user on your <code>gp-server</code> (it could be your
localhost, or a different server on your local network), and copy or clone the
binaries into its home directory:</p>

<pre><code># useradd gp
# git clone git://github.com/sitaramc/gitpod.git /home/gp/bin
</code></pre>

<p>Then change its default shell:</p>

<pre><code># chsh gp -s /home/gp/bin/gitpod
</code></pre>

<p>Now you can proxify any git repository from your shell by simply running:</p>

<pre><code>$ ssh gp@gp-server clone URL reponame
</code></pre>

<p>The result with the <a href="https://github.com/symfony/symfony">Symfony repository</a>:</p>

<pre><code>$ ssh gp@gp-server clone git://github.com/symfony/symfony.git symfony
running: git clone --progress --mirror git://github.com/symfony/symfony.git
Cloning into bare repository symfony.git...
...skipping cloning command...

$ time git clone git://gp@gp-server/symfony.git
Cloning into symfony-new...
fetching from git://github.com/symfony/symfony.git
remote: Counting objects: 141630, done.
remote: Compressing objects: 100% (41715/41715), done.
remote: Total 141630 (delta 89896), reused 135418 (delta 84468)
Receiving objects: 100% (141630/141630), 21.11 MiB | 14.19 MiB/s, done.
Resolving deltas: 100% (89896/89896), done.

real    0m9.090s
user    0m2.152s
sys     0m1.776s
</code></pre>

<p>It takes less than 10 seconds to clone the Symfony sources into my local
computer (once I previously cloned it in Gitpod).</p>

<p>To use this git repository with into your project, just add the corresponding
repository section into your <code>composer.json</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "require": {
        "symfony/symfony": "dev-master"
    },
    "repositories": [
        {
            "type": "vcs",
            "url":  "git://gp@gp-server/symfony.git"
        }
    ]
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now the <code>php composer.phar install</code> command will directly clone your local
repository instead of fetching GitHub.</p>

<p>Not to end up with lots of unmeaningful repositories in your <code>composer.json</code>,
you can use <a href="http://getcomposer.org/doc/articles/handling-private-packages-with-satis.md">Satis</a> to reference all of your local proxies. Satis is usefull
when you want to declare private repositories for your project, but in this
case you can use it to <strong>overload</strong> any public repository with your proxy.
Then you only have to add the Satis URI in your <code>composer.json</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "repositories": [
        {
            "type": "composer",
            "url": "http://packages.example.org/"
        }
    ],
    "require": {
        "symfony/symfony": "2.1.*"
    }
}
</code></pre>

<h2 id="using-broker">Using Broker</h2>

<p>I recently discovered <a href="https://github.com/researchgate/broker">Broker</a>, a PHP application which creates a full
repository proxy for Composer.</p>

<p>Like the previous method, you have to initialize your proxy with the desired
vendors before running a <code>composer install</code> in your project. However Broker
has the advantage to directly take your <code>composer.json</code> as the reference, and
download all your vendors <strong>as Composer do</strong>. So it not only works for git
repositories, but also with archives (and everything Composer can manage).
Finally, it operates like Packagist or Satis, by providing a <code>packages.json</code>
with just the libraries you need.</p>

<p>To make it work, the <a href="https://github.com/researchgate/broker#readme">README</a>
is really clear:</p>

<pre><code>$ git clone git://github.com/researchgate/broker.git
$ cd broker
$ curl -s https://getcomposer.org/installer | php
$ php composer.phar install
$ php broker.php broker:add project_name path/to/project/composer.json
</code></pre>

<p>This will download all your vendors into the <code>repositories/project_name</code>
folder. Once you've set up your server to point on the root directory of
Broker, you could had it to your <code>composer.json</code> file:</p>

<pre><code class="json">{
    "repositories": [
        {
            "type": "composer",
            "url": "http://broker-server/repositories/project_name"
        }
    ],
    "require": {
        "symfony/symfony": "2.1.*"
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>I would recommend this method which is much easier than the previous one, and
also much more powerfull as it is provided for Composer. However, keep in mind
to update your proxy repositories first before running a <code>composer update</code>.</p>

<h2 id="the-missing-option">The missing option</h2>

<p>Both of the previous methods work, but they have the same major incovenient:
you have to modify the <code>composer.json</code> to use the proxy. In the case of
a private project for your company it is not a real problem as every developer
will use the company proxy. But it can be more problematic on an open source
project as the file will <strong>no longer be shareable.</strong></p>

<p>In my opinion, that would be a nice option for Composer to use a local proxy:</p>

<pre><code>$ php composer.php install --proxy http://composer-proxy.local/
</code></pre>

<p>Or event use a local folder to download the vendors before copying them to
your project:</p>

<pre><code>$ php composer.php install --proxy /path/to/cache
</code></pre>

<p>In that case, Composer will explicitly tell the proxy what vendors to
clone/download, and then it will download/copy the needed ones in your
project. Thereby, every developer using the same proxy will save time and
bandwidth, and even you, if you are working on several projects on your
machine, will be able to download vendors only once.</p>

<p>What do you think about that?</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
      <entry>
      <title type="html"><![CDATA[How to create a blog in less than a minute]]></title>
      <link href="https://moquet.net/blog/create-a-blog-in-less-than-a-minute"/>
      <updated>2012-08-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://moquet.net/blog/create-a-blog-in-less-than-a-minute</id>
      <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote>
  <p>Yo dawg! I heard you like blogs. So I started a blog and blogged about how to
  create a new blog. So you can learn to blog while reading this blog.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hi everyone! I'm Matthieu Moquet, a french PHP web developer, currently
working on the future of the awesome <a href="http://www.blablacar.com/">BlaBlaCar</a> startup. To introduce myself
in a few words, I'm a <a href="http://symfony.com/">Symfony</a> lover, an <a href="http://developer.android.com/">Android</a> fanboy, an intensive
<a href="http://git-scm.com/">git</a> &amp; <a href="http://www.vim.org/">vim</a> user, and this blog will be all about that.</p>

<p>For my very first article, let's see <strong>how this blog was created</strong>, in a very
simple way, using <a href="http://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a>.</p>

<p>Jekyll is a simple <strong>static site generator</strong>. It will transform all your HTML
&amp; markdown/textile content into ordered HTML files. It allows you write articles in
simple text files and create static HTML pages, but without repeating the
layout of your site.</p>

<h2 id="prerequisites">Prerequisites</h2>

<p>You must:</p>

<ul>
<li>be able to <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Install">install Jekyll</a>: <code>sudo gem install jekyll</code></li>
<li>know basic markup languages such as <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTML">HTML</a>, <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Markdown">Markdown</a>, and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/YAML">Yaml</a></li>
<li>know Git and have an account on <a href="http://github.com">Github</a> (optional but useful to make it
online)</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="initialize-the-structure">Initialize the structure</h2>

<p>First we're going to create the basic structure of our app. The content of each
folder we need is described in <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/usage">Jekyll Usage page</a>:</p>

<pre><code>$ mkdir _layouts _posts
$ touch index.html _config.yml _layouts/{default,post}.html
</code></pre>

<p>You can customize the default <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/configuration">configuration</a> by editing the
<code>_config.yml</code> file. For now, let's configure the permalinks of each post, with
the date and the slug. There is an option to make pretty URLs automatically:</p>

<pre><code>permalink: pretty
</code></pre>

<h2 id="create-a-basic-layout">Create a basic layout</h2>

<p>Let's have something to watch! We'll now create the layouts and the homepage.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>_layouts/default.html</code> will contain our main layout (header, body &amp; footer)</li>
<li><code>_layouts/post.html</code> will overload the default one to had the structure of
the article (a title, some metadata and a body)</li>
<li><code>index.html</code> will contain what we want to show on our homepage (for instance,
the list of all blog posts)</li>
</ul>

<p>Now what about the content? Jekyll offers you <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Template-Data">several variables</a> to
display your content. It uses the <a href="https://github.com/shopify/liquid/wiki/liquid-for-designers">Liquid templating</a> system to display
them. If you're familiar with templating engine like Twig or Jinja, you should
feel confortable with it.</p>

<p>The <em>inheritance</em> system works by using the <code>content</code> variable in the layout
file, which will be replaced by the content of the file using this layout.
Specifying a layout can be done in the <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/YAML-Front-Matter">Front Matter</a> of any file.</p>

<p>Lets see an example of a basic structure:</p>

<p><code>_layouts/default.html</code>: defines the basic structure</p>

<pre><code class="html">&lt;!DOCTYPE HTML&gt;
&lt;html lang="en"&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;My Blog&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
    {{ content }}
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p><code>index.html</code>: defines the homepage where we list all blog articles</p>

<pre><code class="html">---
layout: default
---

&lt;h1&gt;Blog post&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
    {% for post in site.posts %}
        &lt;li&gt;
            {{ post.date|date_to_string }} »
            &lt;a href="{{ post.url }}"&gt;{{ post.title }}&lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
    {% endfor %}
&lt;/ul&gt;
</code></pre>

<p><code>_layouts/post.html</code>: defines the post layout</p>

<pre><code class="html">---
layout: default
---

&lt;article class="post"&gt;
    &lt;header&gt;
        &lt;h2&gt;{{ page.title }}&lt;/h2&gt;
        &lt;time datetime="{{ page.date|date: "%Y-%m-%d" }}"&gt;
            {{ page.date|date_to_string }}
        &lt;/time&gt;
    &lt;/header&gt;

    &lt;div class="entry"&gt;
        {{ content }}
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/article&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>And then I just have to add a new markdown file in the <code>_posts</code> directory
(following the convention <code>YYYY-MM-DD-slug-of-the-post.markdown</code>) to add a new
blog post:</p>

<pre><code class="html">---
layout: post
title: This is an example
---

Hi folks! This is an example of content.
</code></pre>

<p>That's it! We've created a blog in a few lines. You're now ready to <a href="https://help.github.com/articles/using-jekyll-with-pages">push it
online on GitHub</a>.</p>

<h2 id="go-further">Go further</h2>

<p>Of course, Jekyll has a lot more features not presented in this article. The
best way to learn is to have a look at the many <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Sites">sites using
Jekyll</a>.</p>

<p>Here are some quick improvements you can do:</p>

<ul>
<li>enable <strong>RSS feeds</strong> by adding an <a href="https://github.com/MattKetmo/mattketmo.github.com/blob/master/atom.xml">atom.xml</a> file</li>
<li>enable dynamic comments with services like <a href="http://disqus.com/">Disqus</a> or <a href="http://www.livefyre.com/">Livefyre</a> (javascript only)</li>
<li>use code highlight with <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Liquid-Extensions">Pygments</a></li>
</ul>

<p>There are also plenty of <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll/wiki/Plugins">plugins</a> (written in ruby) you can use.</p>

<p>To simplify the installation of Jekyll, you can even use <a href="http://jekyllbootstrap.com/">JekyllBootstrap</a> which
will initialize the structure for you and put it on your Github account. It
has several themes you can use if you don't want to play with CSS.</p>

<p>I also recommend to read <a href="http://tom.preston-werner.com/2008/11/17/blogging-like-a-hacker.html">how Jekyll was born</a>, a nice article by its
creator which will give you a better understanding of the spirit of static blog
generators like Jekyll.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
  </feed>